Usually I like working in my shop,
انا عادة احب العمل في متجري
but when it's raining and the driveway outside turns into a river,
لكن عندما تبدء الامطار بالهطول و تتحول الطرقات الى انهار
then I just love it.
فانني بالفعل احب ذلك
And I'll cut some wood and drill some holes and watch the water,
وسوف اقوم بقطع بعض الخشب وحفر بعض الثقوب ومشاهدة المياه
and maybe I'll have to walk around and look for washers.
بل ربما سوف اخذ جولة في الارجاء باحثا عن الغسالات
You have no idea how much time I spend.
انتم لا تتملكون اية فكرة عن الوقت الذي امضيته
This is the "Double Raindrop."
هذا هو ما يعرف بقطرات المطر المزدوجة
Of all my sculptures, it's the most talkative.
من ضمن جميع منحوتاتي، هذا هو الاكثر تفضيلا و حدثيا
It adds together the interference pattern
انه يضيف نمط التداخل
from two raindrops that land near each other.
الذي نشهده من قطرتي مطر تهطلان بالقرب من بعضهما البعض
Instead of expanding circles, they're expanding hexagons.
حيث انه بدلا من ان يشكلا دوائر فانهما يشكلان سداسيات
All the sculptures move by mechanical means.
جميع هذه المنحوتات تتحرك بواسطة وسائل ميكانيكية
Do you see how there's three peaks to the yellow sine wave?
هل ترون كيف انه هناك ثلاث قمم لموجة اقتران الجيب ذي اللون الأصفر؟
Right here I'm adding a sine wave with four peaks and turning it on.
هنا أنا أضيف موجه اقتران جيب ذات أربع قمم واقوم تشغيلها
Eight hundred two-liter soda bottles --
ثمانمائة علبة من الصودا ذات سعة ال 2 لتر
oh yea.
أوه نعم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Four hundred aluminum cans.
اربعمائة علبة من الالمونيوم
Tule is a reed that's native to California,
تول هو نوع من القصب الذي يعود اصله الى كاليفورنيا
and the best thing about working with it is that it smells just delicious.
و من افضل الاشياء اثناء العمل به ان رائحته شهية
A single drop of rain
قطرة واحدة من المطر
increasing amplitude.
تزيد المدى
The spiral eddy that trails a paddle on a rafting trip.
الدوامة اللولبية هي التي تحرك المسارات في رحلة تجديف واسعة
This adds together four different waves.
هذا التموج ناتج من جمع اربع موجات مختلفة
And here I'm going to pull out the double wavelengths
وهنا سوف اسحب اطوال الموجات المزدوجة
and increase the single.
و ازيد من من اطوال الموجات الفردية
The mechanism that drives it has nine motors
الالية التي تحرك هذا التموج لديها تسع موتورات
and about 3,000 pulleys.
و حوالي ثلاثة الاف بكرة
Four hundred and forty-five strings in a three-dimensional weave.
اربعمائة و خمسة واربعين خيط في نسيج ثلاثي الابعاد
Transferred to a larger scale --
نقلت الى نطاق اوسع
actually a lot larger, with a lot of help --
في الحقيقة لقد نقلت الى نطاق واسع جدا و ذلك بكتير من المساعدة
14,064 bicycle reflectors --
اربعة عشر الفا و اربعة و ستين دراجة عاكسة
a 20-day install.
عشرون يوما للتنصيب
"Connected" is a collaboration
متصل هو ثمرة تعاون
with choreographer Gideon Obarzanek.
مع مصممة الرقصات جديون اوبرزانيك
Strings attached to dancers.
الخيوط متصلة مع الراقصن
This is very early rehearsal footage,
هذه لقطات بروفة تحضيرية في المراحل المبكرة جداً
but the finished work's on tour
لكن العمل النهائي عرض في جولة
and is actually coming through L.A. in a couple weeks.
وهو قادم عن طريق لوس انجلوس في بضعة اسابيع
A pair of helices and 40 wooden slats.
زوج من الواللب و 40 قضيب من الخشب
Take your finger and draw this line.
خذ إصبعك وارسم هذا الخط
Summer, fall, winter, spring,
الصيف، الخريف، الشتاء، الربيع
noon, dusk, dark, dawn.
الظهر، الغسق، الظلام، الفجر
Have you ever seen those stratus clouds
هل صادف وان شاهدتم تلك الغيوم الطبقية
that go in parallel stripes across the sky?
التي تسير في خطوط متوازية عبر السماء؟
Did you know that's a continuous sheet of cloud
هل تعلم أن هذه هي الصحيفة المستمرة من السحب
that's dipping in and out of the condensation layer?
التي تغطس داخلة و خارجة من طبقة التكاثف؟
What if every seemingly isolated object
ماذا لو كان كل جسم يبدو معزولا
was actually just where the continuous wave of that object
كان في الواقع مجرد موجة مستمرة من هذا الكائن
poked through into our world?
مارة عبر عالمنا؟
The Earth is neither flat nor round.
الأرض ليست مسطحة ولا مستديرة
It's wavy.
انها متموجة
It sounds good, but I'll bet you know in your gut that it's not the whole truth,
كل ذلك يبدو جيدا، ولكن أراهن أنكم تعرفون في داخلكم انها ليست الحقيقة بكاملها
and I'll tell you why.
و انا سأخبركم لماذا
I have a two-year-old daughter who's the best thing ever.
لدى طفلة تبلغ من العمر عامين وهي أفضل شيء عندي على الإطلاق
And I'm just going to come out and say it:
وانا سوف اتجرا واقول
My daughter is not a wave.
بان ابنتي ليست موجة
And you might say, "Surely, Rueben, if you took even just the slightest step back,
اعلم انكم ستقولون: بالتاكيد روبين! لو انك أخذت حتى مجرد أدنى نظرة للوراء
the cycles of hunger and eating,
حلقات الجوع والأكل
waking and sleeping, laughing and crying
المشي والنوم، الضحك و البكاء
would emerge as pattern."
فسوف تظهر وكأنها نمط
But I would say, "If I did that,
لكني ساقول: بانني لو فعلت ذلك
too much would be lost."
فإن الكثير سوف يضيع
This tension between the need to look deeper
هذا التوتر بين الحاجة إلى نظرة أعمق
and the beauty and immediacy of the world,
والجمال والآنية في هذا العالم
where if you even try to look deeper you've already missed what you're looking for,
التي إذا حاولت ان تنظر فيها بشكل اعمق، فإنك بالفعل سوف تضيع ما كنت تبحث عنه
this tension is what makes the sculptures move.
هذا التوتر هو ما يجعل هذه المنحوتات تتحرك
And for me, the path between these two extremes
وبالنسبة الى، فإن الطريق بين هذين المتطرفين الاثنين
takes the shape of a wave.
يأخذ شكل الموجة
Let me show you one more.
اسمحوا لي ان اريكم واحدة اخرى
Thank you very much. Thanks.
شكرا جزيلا. شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thanks.
شكرا.
June Cohen: Looking at each of your sculptures,
جون كوهن: بالنظر الى كل من التماثيل الخاصة بك
they evoke so many different images.
فإنها تستحضر صورا كثيرة ومختلفة
Some of them are like the wind and some are like waves,
بعضها يبدو مثل الرياح و البعض الاخر مثل الموجات
and sometimes they look alive and sometimes they seem like math.
واحيانا تبدو كانها حية و في احيان اخرى تبدو كانها رياضيات
Is there an actual inspiration behind each one?
فهل هناك الهام حقيقي خلف كل واحدة منها؟
Are you thinking of something physical or somthing tangible as you design it?
هل تفكر في شي مادي ام شي ملموس وانت تصمم هذه المنحوتات؟
RM: Well some of them definitely have a direct observation --
ر.أم: في الحقيقة، فإن بعضا منها بالتأكيد هو نتيجة لمشاهدة مباشرة
like literally two raindrops falling,
تماما مثل قطرتي المطر الهاطلتين
and just watching that pattern is so stunning.
حيث ان مشاهدة هذه النمط لوحده هو امر مذهل جدا
And then just trying to figure out how to make that using stuff.
ويلي ذلك مجرد المحاولة لمعرفة كيفية تحقيق ذلك النمط باستخدام الاشياء.
I like working with my hands.
انا احب العمل بيدي
There's nothing better than cutting a piece of wood
لا يوجد شيء أفضل من قطع قطعة من الخشب
and trying to make it move.
ومحاولة جعلها تتحرك
JC: And does it ever change?
وهل حصل وان تغير ذلك؟
Do you think you're designing one thing,
هل تعتقد بانك في وقت ما كنت تصمم شيئا معينا
and then when it's produced it looks like something else?
وبدا بعد ان انتهيت من صنعه بأنه شيء اخر؟
RM: The "Double Raindrop" I worked on for nine months,
قطرة المطر المزدوجة التي عملت عليها لتسعة اشهر
and when I finally turned it on,
واخيرا عندما قمت بتشغيلها
I actually hated it.
فاني حقيقة كرهتها
The very moment I turned it on, I hated it.
لقد كرهت تلك اللحظة التي قمت بتشغيلها فيها
It was like a really deep-down gut reaction, and I wanted to throw it out.
كانت مثل رد فعل الامعاء اثناء حركتها، وكنت أرغب في رميها
And I happened to have a friend who was over,
وصدف انه كان بالقرب مني صديق
and he said, "Why don't you just wait."
فقال لي: لماذا لا تتنتظر
And I waited, and the next day I liked it a bit better,
وانتظرت، وفي اليوم التالي فإنها أعجبتني قليلا
the next day I liked it a bit better, and now I really love it.
وفي اليوم التالي اعجبتني أكثر، والآن فأنا حقا أحبها
And so I guess, one, the gut reactions a little bit wrong sometimes,
ولذا فانا أعتقد، اولا، أن ردود الفعل الاولية خاطئة في بعض الأحيان
and two, it does not look like as expected.
وثانيا، فأنها لا تبدو كما هو متوقع.
JC: The relationship evolves over time.
العلاقة تتطور مع مرور الوقت
Well thank you so much. That was a gorgeous treat for us.
شكرا جزيلا لكم أيضا. وكان ذلك رائعا لنا
RM: Thanks. (JC: Thank you, Reuben.)
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)